Well, before we do a postmortem on what happened, let's just quickly look at the standing the ranking
사후 조사를 하기 전에 순위표부터 간단히 살펴보죠
So you'll remember that when we did a constant run based on the average, we had an error, an average
기억하실 거예요 평균에 기반해 지속 실행을 했을 때 오류가 있었죠 평균 예측
prediction difference of 146.
차이가 146였어요
When we did traditional machine learning, it went to 139.
전통적인 머신 러닝 때는 139까지 올라갔어요
Random forest was 97.
랜덤 숲은 97이었어요
The human, one human in particular, uh, who shall not be named, was 127, uh, GPT four or mini
참가자 중 특히 한 명은 이름을 밝힐 수 없어요 127달러였죠 GPT 4라고 불리는 미니였는데 처음
when we ran it the first time, I'm afraid to say was $80.
실행했을 때 80달러였던 것 같아요
GPT four was 76, and what we just came back with was 91.
GPT 4는 76이었고 방금 나온 건 91이었어요
As I say, there were things about it that actually were improved on the prior run, but for whatever
아까도 말했지만 이전 주행에서 개선된 점이 있지만 이유가
reason, uh, it is what it is.
뭐든 어쩔 수 없죠
I can't I can't fudge the results.
결과를 조작할 순 없어요
The unfortunately, the business metric that we're most focused on was slightly poorer fine tuning,
안타깝게도 우리가 가장 집중하는 사업 지표가 약간 부족합니다 세밀
uh, has, uh, fine tuned in the wrong direction, it seems.
조정이 잘못된 방향으로 이뤄진 것 같아요
So let's talk about that.
그 얘길 해보죠
It was obviously a sobering moment for us, an important learn on our journey.
정신이 번쩍 드는 순간이었어요 여정에서 중요한 걸 배웠죠
Uh, so it does, uh, take a moment.
시간이 좀 걸리네요
We need to take a moment to think about, um, what is the objective of fine tuning with a frontier
잠시 생각을 해봐야겠어요 개척지 모델을 세밀하게 조정하는 목표가
model?
뭘까요?
Uh, fine tuning is often used, and we will be using it for taking an open source model that has fewer
미세 튜닝을 자주 사용하는데 매개 변수가 적은 오픈 소스 모델을 선택해 프런티어
parameters and trying to train it on a data set to make it rival with a frontier model.
모델에 대적할 수 있도록 데이터 세트에서 훈련할 거예요
But when you have a frontier model that has trillions of parameters already and has been trained over
하지만 수조 개의 매개 변수가 이미 있고 방대한 데이터 세트를 위해 훈련된
enormous data sets, what is your objective?
개척자 모델이 있다면 목표가 무엇일까요?
Um, and so here, these, these five main objectives for why you fine tune a frontier model.
개척 시대 모델을 조정한 다섯 가지 주요 목적이 있어요
I actually basically took these from OpenAI's website itself.
오픈AI의 웹사이트에서 가져온 것들이에요.
These are OpenAI's reasons for why you would want to train to fine tune something like GPT for many.
오픈라이에서는 GPT 같은 기능을 세밀하게 조정하는 훈련을 실시하죠
Um, and it's, it's if you want to craft the like the style or tone of the responses, it gives an
반응의 스타일이나 톤을 만들고 싶을 때 반응에 빈정거림을
example of adding some sarcasm to some responses.
추가하는 예가 되죠
If you want to improve reliably producing a particular type of format, a construct, you need the format
특정 형식의 형식, 구성체를 신뢰할 수 있게 제작하고 싶다면 특정한 스타일,
to be in a particular style or way or structure.
방법, 구조에 있는 형식이 필요해요
Um, the third one is correcting, uh, where the model is failing to follow a difficult or challenging
세 번째는 수정입니다 어렵거나 어려운 프롬프트를 따르지 않는 모델이죠
prompt.
아주 복잡한 걸 요구하는데 Get it은 농담을 이해하지 못해요
Um, handling edge cases when there are things that are occasional flaws that get exposed in the model
첨단 케이스 처리란 때때로 노출되는 결함이 있는 경우죠 그걸 수정하고
that you need to correct for and then performing something new.
새로운 걸 실행해야 하는 모델에서요 Get up
And this is perhaps what we were trying to do, a new task, but one that's hard to articulate in a
그게 우리가 하려던 일이었어요 새로운 작업이었지만 바로 설명하긴 어려웠죠
And that's really what OpenAI stresses on the site that it's about trying to solve for things that you
오픈AI가 사이트에서 강조하는 게 바로 그겁니다 프롬프트만으로 고칠 수
can't already fix with good prompting, and it really urges you to start by working as much as you can
없는 문제를 해결하려고 노력하죠 프롬프트에서 최대한 많은 작업을 하도록 강력하게
on the prompt, because much of the time with something like GPT four or mini, you're going to be able
권장합니다 GPT 4, 미니 같은 것들은 대부분 프롬프트만으로
to get to a very high level of performance just through prompting.
아주 높은 수준의 실행을 얻을 수 있거든요
Um, and really, for a frontier model that that's the key here.
개척지 모델로서는 그게 핵심이에요
Uh, the we can already specify the question at hand and the style of output very clearly in a prompt.
이미 당면한 질문과 프롬프트에서 결과물의 스타일을 명시할 수 있어요
And in fact, if you remember back to the prior results, GPT four mini responded accurately in terms
이전 결과를 떠올려 보면 GPT 4 미니는 적절한 구조라는 측면에서 정확하게
of a proper structure.
반응했죠
In every single case, it never we weren't ever not able to pluck a number out.
모든 사건에서 숫자를 추려내지 못한 적이 없어요
And the numbers were always, you know, within within an error close ish to the product.
숫자는 항상 오차 범위 내에 제품에 근접해 있었어요
It was guessing, um, so it wasn't a problem with it understanding the challenge or the output format.
추측이었죠, 그래서 챌린지나 출력 형식을 이해하는 데는 문제가 없었어요
Um, and you have to remember that GPT four and GPT four mini have an absolutely staggering size of
GPT4와 GPT4 미니는 엄청난 규모의 훈련 데이터를 가지고 있습니다
training data with a great world knowledge, and it's unlikely that giving it 500 more training examples
세계 지식이 담겨 있죠 500개의 훈련 예시를 더 제공한다고 세계 지식이
is going to move the needle in terms of its world knowledge.
달라질 것 같진 않아요
And there is then this, this slight point, um, that, uh, that I talked about a while back now about
그리고 사소한 문제가 있어요 전에 말했던 심각한 건망증에 대한
what they call catastrophic forgetfulness, forgetting, which is where sometimes adding in more fine
건데요 망각이라는 거예요 때때로 미세한 조율을 더하면
tuning causes you to erode some of the deeper knowledge that was gained during pre-training.
훈련 전에 얻은 깊은 지식이 줄어들기도 하죠
So it's not always a good thing to be fine tuning.
세세한 부분까지 신경 쓰는 게 늘 좋은 건 아니에요
Um, and I don't know if it was catastrophic forgetting that caused this, this slight dip down or whether
엄청난 망각이 원인이었는지 약간 하락했는지도 모르고 시스템에
it's just a bad luck, just that there is some some noise in the system and and it just didn't happen
소음이 있어서 불운이 따랐는지도 몰라요 시험 세트에서 잘 안 풀린
to do so well on the test set.
거죠
Um, but we certainly didn't appear to improve things.
하지만 나아진 건 없는 것 같았어요
That's the bottom line.
그게 핵심이에요
And it's because, in my view, and from from the way that I understand it and the way the experiments
제 관점에서 그리고 제가 이해하는 방식과 실험이 보여주는 방식으로 볼 때 필요한
show, we were already doing a great job of clearly prompting what was needed.
걸 확실히 전달하는 훌륭한 일을 이미 하고 있었기 때문이죠
GPT four, in many, was already understanding that well, and the caliber of results was already very
GPT 4는 이미 많은 사람이 이 점을 잘 이해하고 있었고 그 결과의 수준도 이미 매우 뛰어났죠
So having said that, the challenge for you, though, is to keep working on this.
하지만 당신이 해야 할 일은 계속 작업하는 거예요
I've done a bit of hyperparameter optimization or trial and error to try and improve things a bit.
하이퍼파라미터 최적화 혹은 시행착오를 통해 개선하려고 했어요 비트
Um, but not much.
많이는 아니고요
And I would be shocked if it's not possible to get to a point where this fine tuning is at least doing
조금이라도 나아지지 않는다면 정말 충격일 거예요 적어도 이전 비트보다 조금이라도
a little bit better, a little bit better than what we had before.
나아진다면요 get it get it
So that's the challenge for you.
그게 과제군요
Do some more, you know, I mean, whilst OpenAI doesn't recommend that one puts in massive data sets,
더 많은 것을요 오픈AI는 방대한 데이터 집합을 권장하지
particularly while it's free to do so, I would certainly be interested in in, in trying bigger data
않지만 특히 무료일 때는요 저는 더 큰 데이터 집합을 시도해보고 싶어요
sets.
훈련 데이터 집합을 1,000이나 2,000으로 해봐요
Maybe try some more epochs.
다른 시대를 살아볼 수도 있고요
I did do that and it didn't make a difference for me, but try something different.
해 봤는데 별 차이 없더라고요 다른 걸 시도해 보려고요
There are other hyperparameters you can explore.
다른 hyperperameter도 있어요
You can look up on OpenAI's website.
오픈아이 웹사이트에서 찾아보세요
There's a couple that you can try changing if you wish.
원하면 몇 가지 바꿔볼 수도 있어요
Just pass them into that same dictionary of hyperparameters.
하이퍼파라미터 사전에 넣어 보세요
Um, and uh, yeah, you could also try putting in different training data points, and you can try
다양한 훈련 데이터를 입력해 볼 수도 있고 프롬프트를 플레이해 볼 수도
playing with the prompt.
있어요
I mean, OpenAI's biggest point on the website is that you will get the most mileage from improving
오픈아이가 웹 사이트에서 강조한 점은 입력을 개선함으로써 가장 많은 주행 거리를 얻을 수
the prompting.
있다는 거죠
And obviously this is something where we spent a bit of time curating the data and perfecting the prompts,
데이터 큐레이팅과 프롬프트 수정에서 시간을 좀 들인 부분이죠 하지만 여기서
but there's much, much more that can be done there.
할 수 있는 건 훨씬 더 많아요
So have a shot at that as well.
그것도 한번 해 보세요
The challenge for you is do some hyperparameter optimization, do some playing around with the prompting,
하이퍼파라미터 최적화를 해야 합니다 프롬프트와 관련된 것을 변경해서 더 잘 할
at least do better.
수 있도록 하세요
Let's look back at where we were.
다시 한 번 볼까요?
Your challenge is to do better than 76.
76점 이상을 받아야 해요
Um, and I will tell you that that I have been able to do better than 76 at one point with a with a
그리고 솔직히 말씀드리면 저는 이전 경기에서 76점보다 높은 점수를 받은
prior run.
적이 있어요
And so I have done I know that it's possible to do better than 76 without without making too many changes.
그래서 저는 많은 변화 없이 76편보다 나은 걸 만들 수 있다는 걸 알아요
Not massively better, but better.
많이 나아지진 않았지만 나아졌어요
And that is the challenge for you.
그게 바로 도전 과제죠
Uh, do so please, and let me know how you get on.
그렇게 해요, 어떻게 돼가는지 알려줘요 Get it
And if you particularly if you get, uh, optimized prompt or hyper parameters, then then push the
최적화된 프롬프트나 하이퍼 매개 변수가 있다면 코드를 푸시해 PR을 하세요
code, do a PR so that I can look at it and share it with others and see where we get to.
제가 살펴보고 공유할 수 있도록요 어떻게 되는지 보도록 하죠
Um, and that will be, uh, that will be your your challenge accomplished when you do better than 76.
76점 이상을 받으면 그게 바로 도전 과제의 성적이 되는 거죠
All right.
좋아요
That brings us to a conclusion for week six.
이렇게 6주 차 결론이 났네요
You are remarkably now 75%, three quarters of the way to being an LM engineer, proficient LM engineer
당신은 이제 놀랍게도 75%에 달하는 길을 달렸습니다 능숙한 달 착륙 엔지니어로서 인공지능과
who has mastered AI and LM engineering.
달 착륙 공학에 통달했죠
And I hope you're as excited about that as I am.
여러분도 저처럼 기뻐해 주시면 좋겠네요
It's just a fantastic progress that you should be super proud of everything that you've learned.
정말 멋진 발전이에요 지금까지 배운 모든 걸 자랑스러워해도 돼요
Uh, obviously generating text and code with frontier models assistance and using open source models
프런티어 모델의 도움을 받아 텍스트와 코드를 생성하고 얼굴 껴안기 트랜스포머,
with hugging face transformers, library, uh, lang chain rag.
라이브러리 랑체 같은 오픈 소스 모델을 사용했죠
And then most recently, the five step strategy for problem solving curating data.
최근에는 큐레이터 문제 해결 5단계 전략을 다뤘는데요
We did a lot of curating data.
큐레이팅 데이터를 많이 만들었어요
But you know, the life of an LM engineer involves a lot of data curation.
하지만 달 착륙선 엔지니어의 삶에는 데이터 수집이 많이 포함되죠
That is a knack that you get into, and it's one of the most important parts.
Get it은 요령이에요 가장 중요한 부분이죠
Certainly in all of the experiments that I did, changing the data structure was the thing that moved
제가 했던 모든 실험에서 데이터 구조를 바꾸는 건 바늘을 움직이는
the needle more than anything else.
가장 큰 일이었어요
Uh, and you're already seeing it post a lot of, uh, experiment.
벌써 많은 실험이 post에 올라가 있어요.
Um, but you I'm sure you can do better.
하지만 더 잘할 수 있잖아요
Um, you've played with traditional machine learning.
전통적인 머신 러닝을 사용했죠
Uh, just just to get a good sense of a baseline that that we've beaten comfortably.
Get up 기본값이 얼마인지 확인하려고요 우리가 쉽게 이겼던 점수죠
Uh, you made a frontier model solution, and now fine tuned frontier models.
개척 시대 해결책을 내놓았고 이젠 미세한 개척 시대 모델이 됐죠
So the results were a little disappointing.
그래서 결과가 좀 실망스러웠죠
Gotta be real.
현실적이어야 해요
But nonetheless, this is something that you can use in your own projects.
그럼에도 불구하고 여러분의 프로젝트에 사용할 수 있는 거죠
And there are situations such as if you want to change the style or you're having difficult edge cases
스타일을 바꾸고 싶다거나 어려운 문제가 발생했을
that are causing you problems, then fine tuning is the answer.
때 미세 조정이 답이죠
And now at least you have a good recipe.
그래도 이제 좋은 레시피가 생겼잖아요
You know how to do it and you've seen a run happening.
어떻게 하는지 알고 연승하는 것도 봤죠
You've checked its status, you've watched it in weights and biases.
상태를 확인하고 무게와 편향성을 확인했죠
You know everything that's involved.
다 알고 계시잖아요
All right, next week we turn over a new leaf and we we start a new segment of the voyage as we turn
다음 주엔 새로운 관점으로 여행의 새로운 부분을 시작합니다 오픈 소스
to open source models.
모델로요
Fine tuning open source models is a very different proposition to fine tuning a frontier model, fine
오픈 소스 모델을 미세 조정하는 건 개척지 모델을 미세 조정하는 것과 아주 다른
tuning, an open source model.
제의예요
What we're trying to do is start with something that is massively smaller than the large models that
우리가 하려는 건 우리가 다루는 큰 모델보다 훨씬 작은 모델이에요
I mean, it's still going to have billions of parameters.
여전히 수십억 개의 매개 변수가 있을 거예요
It's still a big model in the in the general scheme of things, but it doesn't compare with the trillions
일반적으로 보면 여전히 큰 모델이지만 GPT4와 GPT4 미니에 있는 수조
of parameters in GPT four and GPT four mini.
개의 매개 변수와 비교할 수는 없어요
So we're going to be fine tuning open source models, and we're going to be using something called Lora,
오픈 소스 모델을 세밀히 조정하고 로라라는 걸 사용할 거예요 들어본 적 있거나 있을
which you may have heard of or you will have heard of because I've mentioned it a few times, but you
거예요 제가 몇 번 언급했거든요 하지만 로라의
may have perhaps seen some examples of Lora, and you may have heard of its cousin, Lora, which is
예시를 본 적도 있을 거예요 로라의 사촌인 로라도 들어봤을 거예요 양자화된
a quantized version of Lora.
버전의 로라죠
We will be working on both, and by the end of it you will know them both back to front.
둘 다 연습할 거예요 끝날 때쯤엔 둘 다 알게 될 거예요
Um, and in the next, next session, we're going to be selecting the base model, which you already
다음 세션에서는 기본 모델을 선택할 겁니다 이미 알고 계시겠지만요
But but we'll be choosing it for reals.
하지만 진짜 선택해야 해요
Um, that is going to be the model that we will have to compete with GPT four.
GPT 4와 경쟁할 수 있는 모델이 될 거예요
Our current the current winner on our leaderboard.
현재 순위표의 우승자는요?
That is going to be our challenge for next week.
다음 주 과제는 그거예요
It's going to be a big challenge, but I can't wait to take it on.
큰 도전이 되겠지만 빨리 시작하고 싶어요
And I hope you can't wait as well.
당신도 기다려주지 않으면 좋겠네요
I will see you then.
그때 봐요